we can now move to the interaction between
the host and the controller so now we are
going to go again through the interrupt
mechanism you should be familiar with it at this
point but before that let's look also at the
alternative way we can have for the cpu and
the controller to coordinate
so the first option this alternative it's
called busy waiting or polling so in
this case it's the host who tries to continuously
access the device let's say a disk for example
through the controller and keeps trying until
it actually manages to get access to it
this is an alternative to the interrupt mechanism
in which is the device that pings or sends
a message to the host when it is available
or when it's done writing or reading data
and so on so if we go for the first option
polling we need of course to define a procedure with
which the host can
initiate input or output transfar with a certain
controller that is connected to a certain
device so we have this handshaking procedure
we need at least two bits to coordinate the
producer consumer relationship between the
controller and the host so we can use the
busy bit in the status register of the controller
so now the controller uses this bit to indicate
its current state to the
host basically to say whether it's
already performing some operation or if it's
free and it can be then used by the host
the host sends signals about the fact that it
wants to interact with the controller through
the comnad ready bit basically it notifies the
controller that a command is available that
is ready and that the host would like to issue that
command to the controller
and then basically this is going to happen in
a loop so the host / the CPU in
our case will keep reading the status register
over and over until the busy bit becomes
clear meaning the device the controller and
the device beyond the control can be used
and now this is not necessarily a bad
idea
so if you have a fast device controller connected
to fast devices and there are good chances
that you can find that the device as free this
actually can reduce time because if you are
lucky and the busy beat is set to zero so it's
clear you can immediately take control of
the device and interact with the device
but of course it becomes quite inefficient
if you have to stay in this loop a lot and
the device is usually busy because then you're
wasting cycles of your CPU trying to get
access to it rather than doing something else
and this is why you commonly go for interrupts
which are the alternative to this so let's
look at that interrupts it's nothing new at
this point it should be at least the concept
so the cpu has a physical wire it has a connection
which is called the interrupt request line
and it senses this line after
executing every instruction this we saw
in the very beginning
of the course if there is indeed
a signal in that line then the hardware
remember always cooperation between
hardware and operating system
the cpu performs a save state and it
does a context it jumps to the interrupt
handler routine at a fixed address in memory
as we will see each interrupt is actually
a number and that number number can be converted
to a specific address
where you will find the set of instructions
that belong to the operating system and
are specific to the interrupt
you get so if you get that and interrupt for
a page fault that interrupt will be translated
into an address in memory
and at that address you will find
the instructions that the operating system
uses to handle a page fault so the interrupt
handler checks what is the cause of the
interrupt it does the necessary processing
let's say if it's a page to locate the page
on disk and then the CPU can go back
running what it
was running before the interrupt so this
is just what I just said you got
different steps here the CPU is initiating
some input output it gets to the controller
and the controller when the input is ready
or the output is completed or if there is
maybe another reason to generate an interrupt
signal maybe an error
it will send such a signal to the CPU and
the CPU will react to that with the interrupt
handler and notice that in between 1 and 4
here the CPU is executing checks for interrupts
between every instruction eventually the CPU
will resume the processing of the
interrupted task and go back to step one
so we say that the device controller raises
an interrupt by asserting a signal on the
interrupt request line the CPU catches the
interrupt and dispatches it to the interrupt handler
and the handler clears the interrupted by
servicing the device
as you can imagine in practice stuff is
always slightly more complicated than what
we discuss in the course so everything we
said so far is true but in practice there
is not a single line for the interrupts because
as you can imagine not all interrupts have
the same importance
a page fault feel really needs to be addressed
as fast as possible while if the user is striking
a key on the keyboard being slightly late
with that does not really make a big difference
from the user perspective so in modern operating
systems there is the ability to defer the
handling of an interrupt if the CPU is already
doing some
critical processing and of course you also
need an efficient way to locate the code that
is defined by the operating system to handle
each interrupt rapidly because of course you
always want to minimize the time spent doing
all this extra work to handle the interrupts
because those are cycles of your cpu that
you are not using to run
a process but you are using to basically
coordinate the processes running the operating
system and so on and we said this in the very
beginning with context switches you really
need to minimize this as much as possible
if you want to have performance
so you have multilevel interrupts in modern
operating system so that are high and low level
priority interrupts and there is of course
dedicated hardware that is going to manage
these different priorities and the interrupts in
your computer so practically you have two interrupt
request lines
one is the one of non-maskable interrupts
so these are serious interrupts serious events
that need to be addressed as fast as possible
and then you have maskable interrupts that
can be turned off by the CPU before the execution
of critical instruction requests
so basically you can physically prevent the CPU
from checking again for interrupts that are
not really important if you know that for
a specific period of time the CPU is running
code that belongs for example to the operating
system to serve a critical interrupt for example
an unrecoverable memory error as we see here
in the slides
this is what I said before so each interrupt
actually carries an address and that address
can be translated or this offset more than an
address that refers to a table of addresses
can be translated into the memory address that
contains the
desired routine to handle and to clear
the interrupt so this is just an example
for an old processor you have here the vector number
that is carried by non-maskable interrupts
and here you can see that for example if
it is14 then that is a page fault
so when I get this number you can go into
the table where you keep the addresses of the routines
and associate 14 with the routine in the operating
system that handles the page fault and then
handling the page fault becomes very fast because
you says the line you immediately switch to
that and everything is done by the hardware
that wakes
up the operating system in a few cycles
now the operating system can interact with
the interrupt mechanism in several ways
so basically it's up to the operating system
which routines are used to react to the specific
interrupts
what happens is that when you have to populate
this table of addresses that are associated
to the different numbers you can get for interrupts
that can be done when you basically boot your
machine because the hardware can probe the
buses you have and check which are the controllers
and then share this information with the operating
system that
can install the corresponding interrupt handlers
during input output hopefully this is clear
now that the device controllers will raise interrupts
when they're ready for service ok and so the
classical example we made before the output
has completed or there is input that is available
or maybe there is a failure